Guide to the Elizabeth Barlow Rogers Papers 1906-2020 (bulk 1960s-2010s) MS 3206
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Professional Papers and Central Park Conservancy Records, 1962-2019
  - Subseries II.D Graphic Materials and Audiovisual Materials, 1968-2011
    - Optical Media from Central Park Conservancy (CPC) (2 of 2) Digital Files, 2005-2009 (Digital file MS 3206)
    - Women to Women Guest Speaker: Elizabeth Barlow Rogers on Landscape Design Betacam SP Tape RESTRICTED, 2001 October 29 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 26)
    - Women to Women Guest Speaker: Elizabeth Barlow Rogers on Landscape Design VHS Tape RESTRICTED, 2001 October 29 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 27)
    - Photos of EBR and Others in Central Park/Central Park Conservancy (2 of 4 folders), 1976-1989 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 29-30)
      These folders contain material by photographer Ruth Orkin.
      For corresponding oversized content see Box 16 Folders 2-3.
    - Photos of EBR and Others in Central Park/Central Park Conservancy (2 of 4 folders), 1973-1996 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 2-3)
      Folders include photographs by Bruce Davidson, Ruth Orkin, Edward Reed, Victor Laredo, Leondard Spencer, and the White House.
    - Photo Book of Bethesda Fountain Restoration, 1981 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 31)
    - Photos of EBR with Central Park Allies, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
    - Portraits of EBR in Central Park, circa 1980 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
    - Photos of EBR with Dignitaries and Important Friends, circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
      Notable subjects include Henry Stern (Former Parks Commissioner of New York City), Mayor Edward Koch, and Mayor David Dinkins.
    - Photos of Central Park by Artist Bruce Davidson, circa 1992 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
    - Photos of EBR with Chinese Delegation in Central Park, circa 1970s (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
    - Contact Sheets of EBR Portraits in Central Park, circa 1980 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
    - Photos of EBR at CPC 10th Anniversary, Portraits, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
    - Contact Sheet and Negatives of Miscellaneous Central Park Activities, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9)
    - Photos and Correspondence from W 100th Street Playground Rededication, 1987 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Photos of ERB and Others in Central Park, 1988, 1990s (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11)
    - Photos from the Central Park Conservancy Archive, 1975-1987 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
    - EBR's Central Parks Conservancy Career Photos (2 folders), 1982-1995 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13-14)
      Notable figures include Mayor Edward Koch, Henry Stern, and Jackie Onasis.
    - Photos from First Frederick Law Olmsted Luncheon and Other Important Events, 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 9, Folder 15)
    - Optical Media on Frederick Law Olmsted, Other Events (1 of 2), 2005-2011 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 16)
      One CD-R "The Gates Reception and Photos," February 16, 2005. Two DVDs: "The Olmsted Legacy: America's Urban Parks"; "The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted. Supplementary series volume 2." Digital access files were created 4/20/2022.
    - Optical Media on Frederick Law Olmsted, Other Events (2 of 2) Digital Files, 2005-2011 (Digital file MS 3206)
    - Betsy Rogers Central Park Tapes 1-4 (two VHS) RESTRICTED, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 17)
      Two VHS tapes with homemade labels: Betsy Rogers Central Park Tapes 1-2 and Tapes 3-4.
    - Think Tank Interview with EBR (VHS) RESTRICTED, 1999 December 12 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 18)
    - A Year in Central Park (VHS) RESTRICTED, 2007 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 19)
    - The Park (VHS) RESTRICTED, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 20)
    - Central Park Slides, 1971-1999 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 24)
    - Central Park Duplicate Slides, 1971-1999 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 25)
    - Negatives and Contact Sheets of Parks Council, 1970 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 17)
    - The Park 16 mm Print with Optical Transfer (Protection Master Betacam) RESTRICTED, 1993 March 10 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 15)
    - A Tribute to Elizabeth Barlow Rogers (VHS) RESTRICTED, 1990 March 28 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 16)
    - Gerald Allen Central Park Architectural Designs, 1980 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 4)
      For related oversized materials see OS-Medium Folder 1.
    - Gerald Allen Designs and Elevations for New Central Park Luminaire. Oversize, undated (Folder OS-Medium, Folder 1)
      For related materials see Box 16 Folder 4.
    - The Central Park Calendar (1987) Photos by Toshi Otsuki (Offsite-box 16, Folder 5)
- Series III. Teaching Materials and Lectures, 1964-2007
  In addition to her literary career and her administrative duties, Elizabeth Barlow Rogers taught courses on landscape design and history and advocated for the teaching of landscape art and architecture. She received her Masters degree in city planning from Yale University in 1964. Some of her coursework and writing from this degree appear in this series. Later, she taught at Columbia University, The Cooper Union, New York Botanical Garden, and the Bard Graduate Center, where she founded and directed a program in Landscape Studies. Papers pertaining to these appointments include lecture notes, slides, correspondence with program administrators, and administrative documents. Other materials include research files published by academic colleagues on related subjects and speeches and lectures on global architecture history and development.
  The collection is arranged in the original order that it was received in. Some materials have been divided into folders from larger groupings for ease of access and preservation of the materials. Related materials are indicated in the finding aid.
  - Lecture I: Introduction to the History of Landscape Design, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
  - Lecture II: Ancient Rome, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
  - Lecture III: Parks, circa 1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
  - Italian Renaissance Lectures and Manuscripts, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
  - Lecture IV: Islamic Manifestations of Paradise, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
  - Lecture V: Princely Gardens, Medieval Manifestations of Paradise and the Rise of Humanism, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
  - Thinking About Landscape: Interdisciplinary Contributions of the 1990s, 1999 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
  - Teaching and Research Materials by Others (1 of 2), 1973-2005 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Teaching and Research Materials by Others (2 of 2), 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
  - Published Materials on Robert Moses, 1964-2007 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Italian Translation of EBR Speech on Central Park, 1988 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 21)
  - Notes and Slides from Landscape Design, 2002 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 22)
  - The Central Park Book and Course, circa 1980 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 9)
  - EBR Coursework at New York Botanical Garden, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
  - Columbia Course: Cities, Parks and Gardens, 1991 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 27)
  - Cooper Union Course, 1991 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 28)
  - Columbia Courses, 1991-1993 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 29)
  - New York Botanical Garden Course, 1992 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 30)
  - Columbia Courses and Extracurriculars, 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 31)
  - Columbia Course Outlines (2 folders), 1991 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 32-33)
  - Teaching Ephemera (Bard Graduate Center, Cooper Union), 1995-2003 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 34)
  - French Classical Gardens, undated (Offsite-box 15, Folder 8)
- Series IV. Awards and Memorabilia, 1906-2017
  Rogers received numerous awards and honors for her career of service to New York City and her achievements in civic life. She also had close ties to her alma mater, Wellesley College, and received recognition as an alumna. Some of her awards were in recognition of the struggle women faced in breaking into leadership roles in public and private life. She saved materials such as award certificates and plaques, invitations and announcements, speeches given by herself and others, and photos of the events. Memorabilia in the collection includes historical prints and artifacts of Central Park, photos of Rogers' family, old resumes.
  The collection is generally arranged in the original order it was received in. Photographs and certificates have been removed from frames whenever possible. Large, three-dimensional items have been rehoused in order to ensure their preservation. Notes of these changes have been made in the finding aid when applicable.
  - Central Parks Conservancy Board of Trustees Resolution in Honor of EBR, 2015 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1)
  - 24 Dollar Award from the Museum of the City of New York, 1986 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 2)
  - Bergdorf Goodman Award, 1970 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
  - YWCA Award, 2000 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
  - EBR Resume, 1989-1995 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5)
  - Awards Programs and Invitations (2 folders), 1981-2012 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6-7)
  - Award Certificates (3 folders), 1984-2005 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 8-9, 17)
  - Parks Conservancy 10th Anniversary Award Dinner Honoring EBR, 1990 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 10)
  - Memorabilia Photos of EBR, Family, 1950s-1970s (Offsite-box 14, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Memorabilia from Public and Professional Life (4 folders), 1990-2017 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 12-15)
  - Historical Central Park Ephemera, 1906-1967 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 18)
  - Publicity and Awards, 2003-2007 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 19)
  - Wellesley Landscape Renewal Memory Book, 2005 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 20)
  - Pugsley Medal Recipients Volume I, 1928-1964 (monograph), 2007 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 21)
  - Pugsley Medal Recipients Volume II, 1965-2007 (monograph), 2008 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 22)
  - Elizabeth and Theodore Rogers CAAF Medal from The Century Club, 2017 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 23)
  - Miami University Honorary Degree Photos, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 24)
    Photos were originally arranged in a small black leather album. They were transfered to archival sleeves in the order they appeared.
  - Maple Leaf Commemorative Plaques from Henry Stern, 1987-1990 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 25)
    Two wooden maple leaf shaped plaques with bronze plates dedicated to EBR by Henry Stern. Housed in individual envelopes.